After May 9, in the housing market,
5月9日之后的房地产市场，
it won't be about home prices so much as
现在与其看房价，
which signals
更要看的是
show up first.
会先出现什么信号。
That's what a lot of people are asking.
很多人都会问。
Will home prices start rising again now?
现在房价会不会再次上涨。
Or will they bounce briefly and turn back down?
还是只是短暂反弹后又掉头。
But the market right now
但眼下的市场，
keeps proving you wrong
如果还是那样
if you look at it
只往一个方向去看，
in just one direction.
就会一错再错。
The reason is simple.
原因很简单。
Right now, the country as a whole
现在全国楼市
is not moving
并不是在
in a single cycle.
按同一条轨迹运行。
Interest rates, regulations, lending, and sentiment
利率、调控、贷款、市场情绪
are all working differently
在不同地区
from one region to another.
都在以不同方式起作用。
So today,
所以今天我们要看的，
instead of asking whether prices will rise or fall,
不是涨还是跌，
we're going to look at
而是哪里会先分化。
where the market will split first.
先从背景
First,
说起。
let's start with the backdrop.
现在的利率
Right now, interest rates
并没有出现
do not look like
大幅下行的迹象。
they're about to fall sharply.
利率持续按兵不动，
When rates stay on hold,
对市场有两层含义。
it means two things
第一。
for the market.
利息负担不会继续
Borrowing costs
急剧恶化。
are not getting worse
但也说明买盘
all that quickly.
还得不到强力推动，
But at the same time,
因为，
financial conditions are not improving enough
金融环境并没有
to push buying demand
明显改善。
that much either.
这才是关键。
That's the key point.
如果贷款条件迟迟不放松，
If lending conditions don't loosen meaningfully,
最终地区之间的差异
regional gaps
只会越来越大。
only get wider.
有真实居住需求支撑的地方，
Places supported by real end-user demand
就能撑住。
will hold up.
投资需求偏弱的地方，
Places with weak investor demand
就会更加承压。
will stay under more pressure.
这里的调控变量
This is where
也非常关键。
the regulatory factor
房地产市场
also matters a great deal.
不是只靠利率
Real estate doesn't move
来驱动的。
on interest rates alone.
贷款限制、税收、
Lending rules, taxes,
以及政策释放的信号，
and policy messaging
都会让市场温度
can immediately change
立刻发生变化。
the market's temperature.
如果市场把它
If the market
解读为调控放松，
reads it as deregulation,
那么先有反应的
expectations
可能不是价格，而是预期。
can react before prices do.
反过来，如果更强调居民负债管理
On the other hand, if household debt controls
和贷款管控，
and tighter lending restrictions
那交易活跃度就可能
are emphasized,
再次收缩。
transaction activity
所以看5月9日之后的市场，
could shrink again first.
重点在于，
So when looking
要先读懂政策信号，
at the period after May 9,
而不是先盯着房价数字。
before you look at price numbers,
政策传递给市场的信号，
you need to read
到底是放松，
the policy signals first.
还是收紧管理。
Is the message being sent to the market
这两者差别非常大。
easing,
接着我们用几种情景
or restraint?
来看。
That difference is enormous.
第一种。
Now let's look
利率停住了，
at the scenarios.
调控压力也不大。
First,
这种情况下，优质区域，
rates have paused,
以及核心地段，
and regulatory pressure is limited.
交易有可能先回暖。
In that case, the most desirable areas
即便价格不会大涨，
and prime locations
也可能先稳住，
could see transactions recover first.
或出现有限上涨。
Even if prices don't jump sharply,
第二种。
they may stabilize first
利率停住了，
or edge up modestly.
但调控加强了，
Second,
或者贷款门槛提高了。
rates have paused,
那买方的观望需求
but regulations tighten
就会重新转向
or the lending bar gets higher.
继续观望。
Then buyers waiting on the sidelines
这时候比起价格，
shift back into wait-and-see mode.
成交量会先降温。
At that point, more than prices,
市场体感上
transaction volume
会变得安静。
cools off first.
第三种。
The market
全国平均表现平淡。
starts to feel quiet.
但北京核心区和
Third,
部分首都圈地区依然强势。
the national average stays muted.
相反，地方城市和外围区域
But Seoul's core districts
则显得疲弱。
and some parts of the metro area stay strong.
这就是一种
By contrast, provincial areas and outer suburbs
彻底分化的市场
remain weak.
持续延续的格局。
That means
我认为现在最现实的，
a fully bifurcated market
就是第三种。
continues.
类似的走势
Right now, I think
其实已经出现过很多次。
this third scenario
即便是在同样的利率环境下，
is the most realistic.
有就业和学区
We've already seen
支撑的地方，
similar patterns
交易就更容易活跃。
many times.
有交通改善预期的区域
Even under the same rate environment,
也会率先反应。
places backed by jobs
反过来，交房供应压力
and strong school districts
较大的地方。
tend to attract
需求基础薄弱的地方。
transactions.
这类区域的恢复速度
Places with expectations of better transit
会慢得多。
also react first.
归根结底，经济和房地产
By contrast, places facing
从来不是分开走的。
a heavy wave of new supply.
利率停住了，
Places with weak demand fundamentals.
也不代表房价
These areas recover
立刻就会上涨。
much more slowly.
有调控出台，
In the end, the economy
也不意味着一定会
and real estate do not move separately.
马上大跌。
Just because rates have paused
真实的市场，
doesn't mean prices
远比这复杂得多。
immediately go up.
收入条件、
And just because new regulations appear
贷款可得性、
doesn't mean the market
区域需求、
automatically crashes.
以及对政策的解读
The real market
都会一起发挥作用。
is far more complex.
所以现在，
Income conditions,
比起一句话判断走势，
borrowing capacity,
更重要的是看
local demand,
你所在的区域
and policy interpretation
落在哪一种情景里。
all move together.
最后总结一下。
So right now,
5月9日之后房价的关键，
more than a one-line forecast,
并不是用
it's much more important
一个词就能回答
to see which scenario
是涨还是跌。
your area falls into.
利率不变，
To sum up,
可以对底部形成支撑。
the key to home prices after May 9
但随着调控和贷款信号的变化，
is not
回暖的区域和
answering in one word
被压制的区域，
whether they'll rise or fall.
会分化得更加明显。
A rate pause
接下来更重要的，
can help support the floor.
不是平均房价。
But depending on regulation and lending signals,
而是成交量、
some areas may recover
贷款走势、
while others
政策信号、
get held back more clearly.
以及各地区供需状况，
What will matter even more going forward
要放在一起看。
is not the average price.
归根结底，市场的变化不是由平均值决定，